<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Maths & Physics Club</title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club" />
<updated>2016-07-31T23:47:56+00:00</updated>
<id>https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/</id>
<author>
  <name>Maths And Physics Club</name>
  <uri>https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/</uri>
  <email>mnp-club-iitb@googlegroups.com</email>
</author>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[BAZINGA Maths!!!]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/events/bazinga-maths/" />
  <id>https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/events/bazinga-maths</id>
  <published>2016-08-11T23:18:04+00:00</published>
  <updated>2016-08-11T23:18:04+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Maths And Physics Club</name>
    <uri>https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club</uri>
    <email>mnp-club-iitb@googlegroups.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Bazinga Maths is a quiz where teams compete to solve an assortment of problems from buzzer round and paradox resolution questions to deep thought problems. While the solutions are based on elementary concepts, they’re sure to test your creativity and challenge your reasoning skills!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;venue--to-be-decided&quot;&gt;Venue : To be decided&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;date-11th-august&quot;&gt;Date: 11th August&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-thursday&quot;&gt;Day: Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;time-900-pm&quot;&gt;Time: 9:00 pm&lt;/h2&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/events/bazinga-maths/&quot;&gt;BAZINGA Maths!!!&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on August 11, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[BAZINGA Maths!!!]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/events/bazing-maths/" />
  <id>https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/events/bazing-maths</id>
  <published>2016-08-11T23:18:04+00:00</published>
  <updated>2016-08-11T23:18:04+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Maths And Physics Club</name>
    <uri>https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club</uri>
    <email>mnp-club-iitb@googlegroups.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;h2 id=&quot;venue--to-be-decided&quot;&gt;Venue : To be decided&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;date-11th-august&quot;&gt;Date: 11th August&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-thursday&quot;&gt;Day: Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;time-900-pm&quot;&gt;Time: 9:00 pm&lt;/h2&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/events/bazing-maths/&quot;&gt;BAZINGA Maths!!!&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on August 11, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[BAZINGA Physics !!!]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/events/bazinga-physics/" />
  <id>https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/events/bazinga-physics</id>
  <published>2016-08-10T23:17:54+00:00</published>
  <updated>2016-08-10T23:17:54+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Maths And Physics Club</name>
    <uri>https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club</uri>
    <email>mnp-club-iitb@googlegroups.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Bazinga Physics is a 4 round quiz where the participant have to rack their brains and use simple intuitive physics concept to solve questions. The questions can be explaining a simple everyday phenomenon to solving some mind-bending thought experiment. Join in and lets enjoy the true essence of physics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;venue--to-be-decided&quot;&gt;Venue : To be decided&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;date-10th-august&quot;&gt;Date: 10th August&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-wednesday&quot;&gt;Day: Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;time-900-pm&quot;&gt;Time: 9:00 pm&lt;/h2&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/events/bazinga-physics/&quot;&gt;BAZINGA Physics !!!&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on August 10, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[BAZINGA Physics !!!]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/events/bazing-physics/" />
  <id>https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/events/bazing-physics</id>
  <published>2016-08-10T23:17:54+00:00</published>
  <updated>2016-08-10T23:17:54+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Maths And Physics Club</name>
    <uri>https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club</uri>
    <email>mnp-club-iitb@googlegroups.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Bazinga Physics is a 4 round quiz (including preliminary or elimination round) where the participant have to rack their brains and use simple intuitive physics concept to solve questions. The questions can be explaining a simple everyday phenomenon to solving some mind-bending thought experiment. Join in and lets enjoy the true essence of physics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;venue--to-be-decided&quot;&gt;Venue : To be decided&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;date-10th-august&quot;&gt;Date: 10th August&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-wednesday&quot;&gt;Day: Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;time-900-pm&quot;&gt;Time: 9:00 pm&lt;/h2&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/events/bazing-physics/&quot;&gt;BAZINGA Physics !!!&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on August 10, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[STAB Orientation For The Freshmen]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/events/stab-orientation/" />
  <id>https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/events/stab-orientation</id>
  <published>2016-08-03T23:17:25+00:00</published>
  <updated>2016-08-03T23:17:25+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Maths And Physics Club</name>
    <uri>https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club</uri>
    <email>mnp-club-iitb@googlegroups.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Orientation for the Freshman on the activities, culture, enthusiasm and achievements of the TECH society in IIT Bombay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;venue-lt-pcsa&quot;&gt;Venue: LT PCSA&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;date-3rd-august&quot;&gt;Date: 3rd August&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-wednesday&quot;&gt;Day: Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;time-500-pm&quot;&gt;Time: 5:00 pm&lt;/h2&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/events/stab-orientation/&quot;&gt;STAB Orientation For The Freshmen&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on August 03, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Summer Of Science (SOS) Project Presentation]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/events/sos-meetup/" />
  <id>https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/events/sos-meetup</id>
  <published>2016-07-28T23:17:02+00:00</published>
  <updated>2016-07-28T23:17:02+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Maths And Physics Club</name>
    <uri>https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club</uri>
    <email>mnp-club-iitb@googlegroups.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Informal Presentation of the Projects done by IIT Bombay students who took up Summer of Science Projects during the summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;venue--new-yoga-room-sac&quot;&gt;Venue : New Yoga Room, SAC&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;date-28th-july&quot;&gt;Date: 28th July&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-thursday&quot;&gt;Day: Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;time-900-pm&quot;&gt;Time: 9:00 pm&lt;/h2&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/events/sos-meetup/&quot;&gt;Summer Of Science (SOS) Project Presentation&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on July 28, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Blackhole Information Paradox]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/blog/blackhole-paradox/" />
  <id>https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/blog/blackhole-paradox</id>
  <published>2016-07-24T10:19:07+00:00</published>
  <updated>2016-07-24T10:19:07+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Toshi Parmar</name>
    <uri>https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Does the baffle still remain?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://space-facts.com/wp-content/uploads/black-hole.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Blackhole&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a talk given on Aug ‘15 at a conference held at Stockholm$^{[1]}$; Stephen Hawking, the well-celebrated british physicist, proposed a resolution of the infamous Information loss paradox, a child of his own theory of Hawking Radiation $^{[2][3]}$ that overturned the widely perpetuated belief that nothing escapes from a black hole’s event horizon. In the interim, this left most of his contemporaries bemused since his theory had no mathematical backbone. A rigorous paper$^{[4]}$ collaborated by Hawking, Malcolm &amp;amp; Strominger in the January of ‘16, humorously entitled ‘Soft Hair on Black Holes’, attempts to pave a mathematical map to resolve the paradox once and for all. But Hawking et al conclude$^{[4]}$ that they’ve just introduced fresh &amp;amp; concrete tools to address the paradox and a complete description still remains an open challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-exactly-is-the-paradox&quot;&gt;What exactly IS the paradox?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The information loss paradox is yet another acclaimed scenario where Quantum Mechanics, describing the subatomic world with the highest precision and General Relativity, equally successful at the cosmic scale, act stubbornly incompatible$^{[10]}$.
General Relativity implies that once a system ‘falls’$^{[5]}$ in the black hole, any information regarding the system can not affect an outside observer, thus for all practical purposes the information is irretrievable. Notice, that we use irretrievable instead of destroyed, i.e. it doesn’t posses a problem if the black hole remains an ever absorbing body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-hawking-radiation&quot;&gt;The Hawking Radiation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around 1975, due to a remarkable connection made by Hawking$^{[6]}$ and Beckenstein$^{[7]}$ between Thermodynamics, Quantum Mechanics and Black Holes, Hawking Radiation came into picture which collapsed the possibility of everlasting black holes to null.
Hawking Radiation stated that black holes, in fact, aren’t as black as we expected them to be. Courtesy to locally small quantum effects$^{[2]}$, (which are ignored in the process of formation and evolution of black holes since the radius of curvature of spacetime outside the event horizon is very large compared to the Planck length$^{[11]}$, the length scale on which quantum fluctuations of the metric are expected to be of order unity) add up to produce a significant effect over the lifetime of the Universe. This simply implies that any black hole will create and emit particles such as neutrinos or photons at just the rate that one would expect if the black hole of M solar masses was similar to a blackbody, with temperature of about $6 × 10^{-8}$/M kelvins$^{[8]}$.
The fact that a black hole will emit photons when none escape is indigestible.
In layman language$^{[9]}$, Quantum Mechanics capacitates a constant potential for “virtual” Particle - Antiparticle pair to be created and annihilated, leaving a net zero state. Same phenomenon at the knife edge of the event horizon permits a possibility when one escapes, while the other plunges immediately into the black hole. Rather than instant annihilation, the “virtual” particle becomes real and escapes; making a petty energy drain on the black hole. The rate at which the energy dissipates from a black hole of M solar masses spares a massive 1071M3 seconds$^{[8]}$ as any black hole’s life period. Any such black hole of mass less than 1015 g would have evaporated by now. Near the end of its life the rate of emission would be very high and about 1030 erg would be released in the last 0.1 s$^{[2]}$. This is a fairly small explosion by astronomical standards but it is equivalent to about 1 million 1 Mton hydrogen bombs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;aftermaths-of-hawking-radiation-theory&quot;&gt;Aftermaths of Hawking Radiation Theory&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to understand why the information loss paradox is a problem, we need first to understand what it is.
Let’s design a thought experiment where a quantum system in pure state enters a black hole. The no-hair (or more aptly, three-hair) theorem$^{[15]}$ compels Hawking radiation to be completely independent of the state of the quantum system entering the black hole. Because part of the information about the state of the system is lost down the hole, the final situation is represented by a density matrix$^{[11]}$ rather than a pure quantum state (which it was, originally). In quantum physics, a scattering matrix or S-matrix is a unitary matrix$^{[12]}$ that maps the scattering channels (the quantum states of system before or after the collision). The scenario could have been picturised as the initial pure state quantum system interacting with a boundary condition and the Hawking radiation as the final scattering channel. But since the transformation from a pure quantum state to a density matrix is non-unitary, this means there is no Scattering-matrix$^{[13]}$ for the process of black-hole formation and evaporation. Or to say, the black hole has performed a non-unitary transformation on the state of system!$^{[14]}$  As you may recall, non-unitary evolution is not allowed to occur naturally in quantum theory because it fails to preserve probability &amp;amp; reversibility.
In layman terms what we start with is a pure state and a black hole of mass M.  What we end up with is a mixed state and a black hole of mass M.  In transforming between a mixed state and a pure state, one must throw away information.  For instance, in our example we took a state described by a set of eigenvalues and coefficients, a large set of numbers, and transformed it into a state described by temperature, one number.  All the other structure of the state was lost in the transformation.
In the face of such evolution, quantum mechanics falls apart, and we are faced with a dilemma.  Do black holes really defy the tenets of quantum theory, or have we missed something in our thought experiment.
Thus, therein lies a paradox!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-way-ahead&quot;&gt;The Way Ahead&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Possible Solutions To The Fate of Black Holes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
There have been many proposed solutions to the paradox, each equally bewildering as another. They are generally classified first into radical options, which require a quantum theory of gravity which has large deviations from semi-classical physics on macroscopic scales, such as non-locality or endowing horizons with special properties not seen in the semiclassical approximation, and conservative options, which do not need such help. Among the conservative options, it is argued that restoring unitary evolution relies on elimination of singularities.$^{[16]}$&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hawking’s leads : Soft Hair on Black Holes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
AdS-CFT correspondence theory$^{[17]}$, a theory launched in 1993, brought what is called as a Holographic Principle into center play in string theory. Holographic principle bestows same properties to universe as its root word indicates, a dimensional reduction. A hologram, which we encounter is a 2-D representation of a 3-D object. Holographic principle was first introduced by G. ‘t Hooft in 1933 as an attempt to a solution to the Information loss paradox and the widely proclaimed war he and L. Susskind had waged against hawking’s earlier claims that information is indeed lost. ‘T Hooft opined$^{[18]}$ that the requirement that physical phenomena associated with gravitational collapse should be duly reconciled with the postulates of quantum mechanics implies that at a Planckian scale our world is not 3+1 dimensional. Rather, the observable degrees of freedom can best be described as if they were Boolean variables defined on a two-dimensional lattice, evolving with time. This observation, deduced from not much more than unitarity, entropy and counting arguments, implies severe restrictions on possible models of quantum gravity. This dimensional reduction implies more constraints than the freedom we have in constructing models. This is the main reason why so-far no completely consistent mathematical models of quantum black holes have been found.
A year later, L. Susskind published a paper, ‘The World as A Hologram’$^{[19]}$, backing up ‘t Hooft’s theory. In July ‘04 Hawking conceded the bet since the AdS/CFT correspondence has shown there is no information loss. Then Hawking set working on the question : How does the information of the quantum state of the infalling particles re-emerge in the outgoing radiation?$^{[1]}$ He proposes that the information is stored, not in the interior of the black hole (as one might expect), but on its boundary, the event horizon. This is a form of holography. Classically, a black hole is independent of its past history. This is also true in the quantum domain. How then can a black hole emit the information about the particles that fell in? The answer, as explained above, is that the information is stored in a supertranslation associated with the shift of the horizon that the ingoing particles caused (Ingoing particles increase the mass of the black hole resulting into an outward shift in the horizon).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;supertranslation&lt;/em&gt;, in layman terms, are the result of a kind of symmetry. In Strominger’s terms$^{[20]}$, Individual light rays can’t talk to each other—if you’re riding on a light ray, causality prevents you from talking to somebody riding on an adjacent light ray. So these light rays are not tethered together. You can slide them up and down relative to one another. That sliding is called a super-translation. It turns out that adding a soft graviton at the event horizon has an alternate description as a super-translation in which you move some of these light rays back and forth relative to one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;supertranslations&lt;/em&gt; form a hologram of the ingoing particles at the horizon(For each particle that goes in, a soft-graviton is added). Thus, the jargon soft hair. The varying shifts along each generator of the horizon leave an imprint on the outgoing particles in a chaotic but deterministic manner. There is no loss of information and Information can be recovered in principle, but it is lost for all practical purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/pdf/1509.01147v1.pdf&quot;&gt;The Information Paradox for Black Holes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[2] &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v248/n5443/abs/248030a0.html&quot;&gt;Black Hole Explosions?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[3] &lt;a href=&quot;http://inspirehep.net/record/101338?ln=en&quot;&gt;Particle Creation by Black Holes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[4] &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/pdf/1601.00921v1.pdf&quot;&gt;Soft Hair on Black Holes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[5] &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wikiwand.com/en/Event_horizon&quot;&gt;Event Horizon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[6] &lt;a href=&quot;http://journals.aps.org/prd/pdf/10.1103/PhysRevD.14.2460&quot;&gt;Breakdown of Predictability in Gravitational Collapse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[7] &lt;a href=&quot;http://journals.aps.org/prd/abstract/10.1103/PhysRevD.7.2333&quot;&gt;Black Holes &amp;amp; Entropy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[8] &lt;a href=&quot;http://math.ucr.edu/home/baez/physics/Relativity/BlackHoles/hawking.html&quot;&gt;Hawking Radiation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[9] &lt;a href=&quot;https://starguyspeaks.wordpress.com/2016/02/21/on-steven-hawkings-new-theory-of-black-holes/&quot;&gt;Wordpress Blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[10] &lt;a href=&quot;http://theory.caltech.edu/people/jhs/strings/str115.html&quot;&gt;The Final Contradiction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[11] &lt;a href=&quot;http://journals.aps.org/rmp/pdf/10.1103/RevModPhys.29.74&quot;&gt;Description of States in Quantum Mechanics by Density Matrix and Operator Techniques&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[12] &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wikiwand.com/en/Unitary_operator&quot;&gt;Unitary Operator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[13] &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wikiwand.com/en/S-matrix&quot;&gt;S-Matrix&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[14] &lt;a href=&quot;http://math.ucr.edu/home/baez/physics/Relativity/BlackHoles/info_loss.html&quot;&gt;Black Hole Information Loss Problem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[15] &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wikiwand.com/en/No-hair_theorem&quot;&gt;No-Hair Theorem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[16] &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/pdf/0901.3156v1.pdf&quot;&gt;Conservative solutions to the black hole Information loss problem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[17] &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/1501.00007.pdf&quot;&gt;The AdS/CFT Correspondence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[18] &lt;a href=&quot;http://xxx.lanl.gov/abs/gr-qc/9310026&quot;&gt;Dimensional Reduction in Quantum Gravity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[19] &lt;a href=&quot;http://xxx.lanl.gov/abs/hep-th/9409089&quot;&gt;The World as Hologram&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[20] &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.scientificamerican.com/dark-star-diaries/stephen-hawking-s-new-black-hole-paper-translated-an-interview-with-co-author-andrew-strominger/&quot;&gt;Interview by co-author Andrew Strominger&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/blog/blackhole-paradox/&quot;&gt;Blackhole Information Paradox&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on July 24, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Brain's Positioning System]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/blog/brain-positioning/" />
  <id>https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/blog/brain-positioning</id>
  <published>2016-06-06T00:01:22+00:00</published>
  <updated>2016-06-06T00:01:22+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Thariq Shanavas</name>
    <uri>https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;h2 id=&quot;ever-wondered-whats-happening-in-our-brains-when-we-get-lost-or-explore-a-new-place-the-nobel-prize-in-physiology-for-the-year-2014-was-awarded-for-some-of-the-answers-to-this-problem-which-had-been-puzzling-scientists-for-almost-a-century&quot;&gt;Ever wondered what’s happening in our brains when we get lost or explore a new place? The Nobel Prize in Physiology for the year 2014 was awarded for some of the answers to this problem which had been puzzling scientists for almost a century.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the GPS in our phones and cars, our brain has a sophisticated positioning system. The brain integrates sensory data and knowledge of our current position to judge where we are headed. Only when we are lost or suffer from neurodegenerative diseases do we realise how critical our positioning system is to our survival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tracking and positioning systems of the mammalian brain was being studied for a long time. For example, the simple roundworm (Caenorhabditis elegans), with just 302 neurons, finds its way around solely by olfactory signals. It follows the path of an increasing or decreasing odour gradient. Honeybees, on the other hand, calculate its position by integrating its direction and speed of movement, without keeping track of landmarks or external cues. Vertebrates have even more sophisticated positioning systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Recent research in the area reveal neural maps in the brains of mammals, which are collections of neurons which fire in specific patterns corresponding to the surroundings and the animal’s position in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2014 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/medicine/laureates/2014/advanced-medicineprize2014.pdf&quot;&gt;Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine&lt;/a&gt; was awarded to Dr. John M. O’Keefe, Dr. May-Britt Moser and Dr. Edvard I. Moser for their discoveries of nerve cells in the brain that enable a sense of place and navigation.
Until the 1930s, research done on lab mice in mazes led to the belief that they memorised a long sequence of lefts and rights to find their way around. Edward C Tolman, physiology professor at the University of California from 1918 to 1954, observed the animals take shortcuts or make detours that would not be expected had they just memorised one long sequence of behaviour. This led to the hypothesis that the rats formed a sort of mental map of its surroundings, corresponding to the spatial geometry around it. Tolman’s ideas remained controversial for decades.
His ideas did not gain much ground up until the 1950s, when it became possible to insert electrodes into the brains of awake mammals to record firing patterns of individual neurons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A cell fires when it triggers an action potential- a short change in the potential difference across the cell membrane.
Dr. John M. O’Keefe studied the brain’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hippocampus&quot;&gt;hippocampus&lt;/a&gt;, a region in the brain associated with memory and spatial navigation (On a side note, the Hippocampus is one of the first regions to be affected by the Alzheimer’s disease). He inserted electrodes into a rat’s Hippocampus, and noticed that certain cells fired when the rat was at a particular location. He called them ‘Place cells’. It was seen that the firing pattern of a handful of such place cells precisely identified the animal’s location. In 1978, O’Keefe and his colleague suggested that place cells were an integral part of the mental map Tolman envisaged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neuroscientists of that era speculated that the hippocampus was too far removed from the sensory cortex (The part of the brain which handles the sensory inputs) to process their information in any meaningful way that could be understood by simple electrodes. O’Keefe’s observations dashed that speculation. It was then hypothesised that the area where place cells were located, namely the CA1 region, in the hippocampus received its location cues from other parts of the hippocampus rather than directly from the sensory cortex.
To verify the hypothesis, O’Keefe and his colleagues disrupted the communication channels between the CA1 region and the region of the hippocampus known to feed information to the CA1. Surprisingly, the neurons in the CA1 fired as before, when the rat reached specific locations. The inescapable conclusion was that the CA1 received its location cues from the entorhinal cortex, an adjoining area of the brain with a direct interface with the hippocampus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Electrodes were inserted into the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Entorhinal_cortex&quot;&gt;entorhinal cortex&lt;/a&gt;, and the firing patterns studied. The cells over there fired much like the place cells, but a single cell also happened to fire at multiple locations! This observation was made in 2002.
By 2005, O’Keefe and his team observed something spectacular about the firing patterns- the locations at which one particular cell fired were the vertices of a regular hexagon! These cells were dubbed grid cells. It was soon apparent that the entire enclosure where the rat was kept was divided into hexagonal grids. As these grid cells were further studied, more patterns were observed- the grid cells in the dorsal side fires at compact hexagons, while those lower down in the ventral side fired at hexagons of larger edge. The different layers of grid cells in the entorhinal cortex fired at hexagons of different size, each layer forming one with approximately 1.4 times the edge length of the hexagon in the layer above. This is strongly reminiscent of the smaller squares and the bigger ones in the Cartesian coordinates.
For example, the top layer fired at hexagons 30 to 35 cm in length, the next layer at 42 to 49 cm, and so on. The lower layers represented hexagons several meters across.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Direction cells and Border cells were also discovered in the entorhinal cortex – the direction cells fire when the rodent faces a particular direction, and the border cells fire when the rat is facing a wall. The firing patterns seemed to reflect the distance from the wall or the edge of an enclosure. In 2008, another long sought out cell was discovered- the speed cells. The firing rates of these cells increased in proportion to its running speed. These cells were believed to provide the grid cells updated information on the rodent’s position.
It was observed that the place cells in the hippocampus rapidly assumes a new location to fire as soon as the rat was put in a new enclosure. However, the grid cells was found to fire at analogous positions in the new enclosure. The grid cells, in some sense, formed a coordinate system that did not change from one enclosure to the other. The firing patterns from the entorhinal cortex was imported to the hippocampus and used to link the place cells to a particular location.
It is now believed that the hippocampus stores not just the position, but also the events that occur at that particular place. Particulars about an event are fused with the coordinates and are laid down in the animal’s memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;However, the scientific world is still pretty much in the dark as to how this information is used by the rest of the brain’s systems or the evolutionary origins of this intricate mechanism. The location systems of the brain and the mechanisms of memory formation will undoubtedly be a fascinating area of research for many years to come.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/blog/brain-positioning/&quot;&gt;Brain&#39;s Positioning System&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on June 06, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Memristors and the Future of Computing]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/blog/memristors/" />
  <id>https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/blog/memristors</id>
  <published>2016-05-31T10:19:07+00:00</published>
  <updated>2016-05-31T10:19:07+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Dhruv Ilesh Shah</name>
    <uri>https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club</uri>
    <email>dhruv.ilesh@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;In 1965, Gordon Moore predicted that the number of transistors in a dense integrated circuit doubles approximately every two years, and since then every manufacturer has been fighting hard to keep up with the Moore’s Law. With the scale of transistor entering sub-20nm, this number is saturating and Moore’s Law has begun to fail us. So what have the scientists and researchers got us? Behold the &lt;i&gt; &lt;b&gt;Memristor&lt;/b&gt;  (a portmanteau of the words memory and resistor)!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original concept for memristors, as conceived in 1971 by Professor Leon Chua at the University of California, Berkeley, was a passive, non-linear, two-terminal electrical component that linked electric charge and magnetic flux. Since then, the definition of memristor has been broadened to include any form of non-volatile memory that is based on resistance switching, which increases the flow of current in one direction and decreases the flow of current in the opposite direction and has since then been thought of as the fourth fundamental electrical component.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Memristors constitute a special type of memory, called the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Resistive_random-access_memory&quot;&gt; ReRAM &lt;/a&gt; or resistive RAM, which works by altering the resistance across a dielectric. The outlook of memristors as memory devices started in 1996, when Stanley Williams, the founding director of the Quantum Science Research Laboratory at Hewlett-Packard, began to look for memory devices that are defect intolerant at the nano scale. And what better way to make a device defect-intolerant than too employ the defects themselves for the job!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; How Memristors Work :&lt;/b&gt; Instead of electrons, memristors use ions as the means of storing information. As the current passes, the holes and defects enable ions of informations to pass through with much greater speed and efficiency - way beyond 1 and 0, to 2, 3 and so on. These levels can be treated as distinct and the demarcation be carried out with ease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; What Does This Mean? &lt;/b&gt; At a lower power consumption than a transistor, a memristor can have multiple levels of representing data (upto 6 levels have been achieved), thus reducing the number of memristors required to perform the same task and who knows - the computer may actually become equipped with base-10 memory soon enough! For example, the largest unsigned binary 64-bit ­integer—18,446,744,073,709,551,615—could be held in 20 bits instead of 64. This not only reduces the number of transistors used, but also the complexity of circuits and ease of NLP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A memristor is often compared to an imaginary pipe that carries water. When the water flows in one direction, the pipe’s diameter expands and allows the water to flow faster – but when the water flows in the opposite direction, the pipe’s diameter contracts and slows the water’s flow down. If the water is shut off, the pipe retains its diameter until the water is turned back on. To continue the analogy, when a  memristor’s power is shut off, the memristor retains its resistance value. This would mean that if power to a computer was cut off with a hard shut down,  all the applications and documents that were open before the shut down would still be right there the screen when the computer was restarted. Isn’t that cool? Although we have been able to cut down the leakage current in conventional transistors, we cannot dare imagine making them as efficient as a prototype of a memristor! This would mean a big revolution in computing, and the best part is that it could be market-ready much before Quantum Computers (which use qubits to store more data-per-bit).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To see how the non-volatile nature and resistive-switching is achieved, check out this video by Stanley Williams: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rvA5r4LtVnc&quot;&gt; The 6 Minute Memristor Guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact Hewlett-Packard has a whole unit devoted to developing ‘The Machine’, &lt;em&gt;using electrons for processing, photons for communication, and ions for storage&lt;/em&gt;, expected to be completed by 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jennifer Rupp, a Professor of electrochemical materials at ETH Zurich,is working with IBM to build a memristor-based machine. Memristors, she points out, function in a way that is similar to a human brain: “Unlike a transistor, which is based on binary codes, a memristor can have multi-levels. You could have several states, let’s say zero, one half, one quarter, one third, and so on, and that gives us a very powerful new perspective on how our computers may develop in the future,” she says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such a shift in computing methodology would allow us to create “smart” computers that operate in a way reminiscent of the synapses in our brains. Free from the limitations of the 0s and 1s, these more powerful computers would be able to learn and make decisions, ultimately getting us one step closer to creating human-like artificial intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;The outcome of this revolution would only be evident by the next decade, but the fact that nano-electronics has enabled us to revolutionarise the micro-electronics industry is a clear signal - to cope up with our growing computing needs, to explore the vastness of Universe, the path goes from within the Nano World! Memristors and Qubits are all set to power the upcoming generations in unfolding the mysteries of our creation, existence and the universe (multiple of them, in fact!)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/blog/memristors/&quot;&gt;Memristors and the Future of Computing&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on May 31, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Generalized Complex Numbers]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/blog/generalised-complex-numbers/" />
  <id>https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/blog/generalised-complex-numbers</id>
  <published>2016-05-17T10:19:07+00:00</published>
  <updated>2016-05-17T10:19:07+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Anish Kulkarni</name>
    <uri>https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Have you ever wondered, why is multiplication of complex numbers defined in such a peculiar fashion and can we do it in another way? Can there be other geometrical interpretations for complex numbers? It turns out, these questions are related and lead to the definition of “Generalized Complex Numbers.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we redefine the multiplication on the set $R\times R$ while preserving certain properties. Addition is defined as before. We desire multiplication to be associative, commutative and distributive. Further we want to satisfy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;(x_1,y_1)\cdot (x,0) = (x\cdot x_1,x\cdot y_1)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is because we still want to interpret (x,0) as a “purely real” number. Thus we can interpret $(x,y)$ as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;(x,y) = (x,0)\cdot (1,0)+(y,0)\cdot (0,1)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The properties of the new multiplication discussed so far allow us to conclude:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;(x_1,y_1)\cdot (x_2,y_2) = x_1x_2 + (0,1)(0,1)y_1y_2 + (x_1y_2 + x_2y_1)(0,1)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, it all boils down to the definition of $(0,1)\cdot (0,1)$ . We may now define:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;(0,1)(0,1)=(p,q)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out, there are only three different ways (unique up to isomorphism as rings) to choose p and q. For example, $q = 0$ and $p = 1 , 0$ or $-1$. The choice $p = -1$ gives us complex numbers that we are familiar with, $p = 1$ gives double numbers while $p = 0$ gives dual numbers. From here on we assume $q = 0$ and $p$ as any real number and the term complex number refers to generalized complex number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Application of dual numbers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we make a rather strange choice $(0,1)^2 = (0,0)$. As a handy notation let $\epsilon  = (0,1)$. So every dual number is of the form a+ɛb and $\epsilon ^2 = 0$. Suppose P(x) is a polynomial over reals. We see that :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;P(a+b\epsilon) = P(a) + b\epsilon P&#39;(a)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where $P’$ denotes the derivative. In fact this is also true for a power series and hence for any analytical function. For example,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\sin (a+b\epsilon) = \sin (a) + b\epsilon \cos (a)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a technique used in Automatic Differentiation in Computer Algebra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geometrical Properties:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let us examine a few geometric properties. Define the complex conjugate of $(x,y)$ to be $(x,-y)$ as before. Notice that $(x,y)(x,-y) = (x^2 – py^2,0)$ is always a “real number”. So we define modulus of (x,y) as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\|(x,y)\| = sqrt(\|x^2 –py^2\|)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A unit circle is then defined as the set $(x,y)$ for $|x,y|=1$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This represents an &lt;em&gt;ellipse&lt;/em&gt; for $p \lneq 0$ (Elliptical number system), a pair of parallel lines for $p=0$ (Parabolic number system) and a pair of conjugate hyperbolae for $p=0$ (Parabolic number system) and a pair of conjugate hyperbolae for  $p \gneq 0$ (Hyperbolic Number system). The argument of a complex number $T(x,y)$ is defined as twice the area of the portion of the unit circle cut out by the ray OT and the real axis, O being the origin (this definition isn’t complete. The attached article gives a fuller account). These definitions give us the beautiful result:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The modulus of the product is the product of the modulus; and the argument of the product is the sum of arguments.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\|z_1z_2\| = \|z_1\|\|z_2\|&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Arg(z_1z_2) = Arg(z_1) + Arg(z_2)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Geometrically, this means that multiplication by a generalized complex number is a rotation in the respective plane followed by scaling. Multiplication by a unit complex number is just pure rotation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Application to Special Relativity and Lorentz Transformation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider $ p=\frac{1}{c^2}$ and let $(t,x)$ and $(t’,x’)$ denote the spacetime coordinates of an event in ground frame and a reference frame moving with velocity $v$ w.r.t. it. Let $z = (1,v)$ and $w$ be the unit complex number $\frac{z}{|z|}$. Then&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;(t,x)\cdot w =  (t&#39;,x&#39;)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, the Lorentz transform in two dimensional Special Relativity is a rotation in the hyperbolic complex plane! This means the modulus doesn’t change under this transform. Which means:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;(ct)^2 – x^2 = (ct&#39;)^2 – x&#39;^2&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also interesting to note that if p=0, (the case of dual numbers), then w = (1,v) is a unit complex number and multiplication by it gives us the Galilean transformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;(t,x)\cdot (1,v) = (t, x+vt )&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find more exciting stuff like trigonometry in various cases $(p\lneq 0, p=0, p\gneq 0)$ and the generalizations of Euler’s formula in the article. Have fun exploring their properties. If you come to know of any other applications of generalized complex numbers, please do share!&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/blog/generalised-complex-numbers/&quot;&gt;Generalized Complex Numbers&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on May 17, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Flexagons]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/blog/flexagons/" />
  <id>https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/blog/flexagons</id>
  <published>2016-05-04T10:19:07+00:00</published>
  <updated>2016-05-04T10:19:07+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Parth Jatakia</name>
    <uri>https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club</uri>
    <email>parth.jatakia@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Flexagons are paper polygons, folded from straight or crooked strips of paper, which have the fascinating property of changing their faces when they are “flexed”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It all began in the fall of 1939. Arthur H. Stone, a 23-year-old graduate student from England, in residence at Princeton University on a mathematics fellowship, had just trimmed an inch from his American notebook sheets to make them fit his English binder. For amusement he began to fold the trimmed-off strips of paper in various ways, and one of the figures he made turned out to be particularly intriguing.
Here’s the video to make a simple hexaflexagon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt; &lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/VIVIegSt81k&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point Stone found the structure so interesting that he showed his paper models to friends in the graduate school. Soon “flexagons” were appearing in profusion at the lunch and dinner tables. A “Flexagon Committee” was organized to probe further into the mysteries of flexigation. The other members besides Stone were Bryant Tuckerman, a graduate student of mathematics; Richard P. Feynman, a graduate student in physics; and John W. Tukey, a young mathematics instructor.
Tuckerman quickly discovered that the simplest way to bring out all the faces of any flexagon was to keep flexing it at the same corner until it refused to open, then to shift to an adjacent corner. This procedure, known as the “Tuckerman traverse,” will bring up the six faces of a hexahexa in a cycle of 12 flexes, but 1,2 and 3 turn up three times as often as 4, 5 and 6. A convenient way to diagram a Tuckerman traverse is shown in Figure 4, the arrows indicating the order in which the faces are brought into view. This type of diagram can be applied usefully to the traversing of any type of flexagon. When the model is turned over, a Tuckerman traverse runs the same cycle in reverse order.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-duGlEV1ddCw/VymMKE9pabI/AAAAAAAAC3c/XlD-a4OvfcE26j6P_9Ya0Ia2gcMR_1AEQCLcB/s1600/flexagon.png&quot; alt=&quot;Flexagon&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video below gives a great visual explanation of the above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt; &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/paQ10POrZh8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now after trying out the simple ones, if you’d want to achieve pro level…..These are some documents you can refer to!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A mathematical investigation of Flexagons can be found here: &lt;a href=&quot;http://delta.cs.cinvestav.mx/~mcintosh/comun/tflexagon/tflexagon.pdf&quot;&gt;Theory of Flexagons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also details about more complicated structures can be found out in the following link. Also you will find some papers written on flexagon on this website (though written in russian).: http://www.flexagon.net/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also if you are a foodie this video will be a heaven for you..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/GTwrVAbV56o&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club/blog/flexagons/&quot;&gt;Flexagons&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;https://stab-iitb.org/math-and-physics-club&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on May 04, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>

</feed>