<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Maths & Physics Club</title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://mnp-club.github.io//feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mnp-club.github.io/" />
<updated>2016-10-28T16:38:45+05:30</updated>
<id>http://mnp-club.github.io//</id>
<author>
  <name>Maths And Physics Club</name>
  <uri>http://mnp-club.github.io//</uri>
  <email>mnp-club-iitb@googlegroups.com</email>
</author>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Algorithmic Biology]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mnp-club.github.io//events/algo-bio/" />
  <id>http://mnp-club.github.io//events/algo-bio</id>
  <published>2016-10-28T04:48:04+05:30</published>
  <updated>2016-10-28T04:48:04+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Maths And Physics Club</name>
    <uri>http://mnp-club.github.io/</uri>
    <email>mnp-club-iitb@googlegroups.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;h3 id=&quot;from-molecules-to-intelligence&quot;&gt;from Molecules to Intelligence!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Algorithmic-Biology-Talk/poster.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A biological cell is nothing but a collection of molecules, yet displays behavior many orders of magnitude more sophisticated than non-biological collections of molecules of the same size, and gives rise to the manifold phenomena of life that we see all around us. This is because the molecular ensembles in cells are self-organized into structures and networks that together execute sophisticated algorithms. This ballet of molecular interactions allows living systems to respond in exquisite ways to their environments, and makes them appear &lt;em&gt;intelligent&lt;/em&gt;. Algorithmic Biology is an emerging discipline which attempts to discover, recreate, and explain biological phenomena from an algorithmic perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;About The Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Professor Manoj Gopalkrishnan has recently joined as an Associate Professor in Electrical Engineer at IIT Bombay. He was previously a faculty member in the School of Technology and Computer Science at TIFR Mumbai. He received his PhD in Computer Science from University of Southern California and BTech in Computer Science and Engineering from IIT Kharagpur. He is broadly interested in connections between Information, Biology, and Physics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;venue--lc-002&quot;&gt;Venue : LC 002&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;date-27th-october&quot;&gt;Date: 27th October&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-thursday&quot;&gt;Day: Thursday&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;time-900-pm&quot;&gt;Time: 9:00 pm&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The talk began with Prof. Gopalkrishnan describing the extent of sophistication achieved by the biological cell and how even a small step towards understanding the details could lead to great advancements. He talked about biochemical reaction networks and how they can be used to model complex statistical phenomena in the simplest of manners - using a &lt;em&gt;soup&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an attempt to show how such analogies can be formed, he discussed a portion of his own work and pitched the &lt;em&gt;chemical soup&lt;/em&gt; against a statistician, for solving a very common problem - parameter optimisiation using &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maximum_likelihood_estimation&quot;&gt;MLE&lt;/a&gt;. The example used was of a triangular die whose outcomes are dependent on 2 unknown parameters. The magic of &lt;em&gt;mass-action kinetics&lt;/em&gt; gives us that the soup converges to Maximum Likelihood Distribution corresponding to the initial conditions known. This is a very non-trivial theorem and professor developed an intuition behind how it works on the basis of the &lt;em&gt;MaxEnt Principle&lt;/em&gt;. The claim that mass-action kinetics maximises entropy, which eventually converges to the MLD of the outcomes is very interesting, and can be seen as &lt;em&gt;Machine Learning&lt;/em&gt; in the soup. In this way, we can also claim that the biological cell is performing &lt;em&gt;“machine learning”&lt;/em&gt; at some extent, which is very fascinating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He went on to explain in what kinds of estimation problems - particularly the log-linear models - the method can be applied, and developed more rigour in the claims. The trick behind the working is derived from topology, toric geometry, information geometry and the MaxEnt Principle of other things. The concepts that go into demostrating this are pretty wide-spread and open new frontiers of inter-disciplinary research!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of the talk, the professor showed how recent advances in computational biology and DNA computing can be mapped onto his research and although we do not know where all this would lead us, it sure is a step - and a whole new &lt;em&gt;nano&lt;/em&gt;-world awaits us!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More on such cool stuff can be found under the banner of &lt;a href=&quot;http://molecular-programming.org/&quot;&gt;Molecular Programming Project&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
You can find Prof. Manoj Gopalkrishnan’s paper on this topic &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1506.03172&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
The slides used in the talk can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/open?id=0BzrafcdwRhiEZFhkeW84b2VfTFM5bWdVYU01eV9yblBqWW5N&quot;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some snaps from the talk! Cheers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt; ![](/images/Algorithmic-Biology-Talk/talk1.1.jpg)  
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;  ![](/images/Algorithmic-Biology-Talk/talk1.2.jpg)   
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;  ![](/images/Algorithmic-Biology-Talk/talk1.3.jpg)   
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io//events/algo-bio/&quot;&gt;Algorithmic Biology&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io/&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on October 28, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Logic GC]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mnp-club.github.io//events/logic-gc1/" />
  <id>http://mnp-club.github.io//events/logic-gc1</id>
  <published>2016-10-12T04:48:04+05:30</published>
  <updated>2016-10-12T04:48:04+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Maths And Physics Club</name>
    <uri>http://mnp-club.github.io/</uri>
    <email>mnp-club-iitb@googlegroups.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io//events/logic-gc1/&quot;&gt;Logic GC&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io/&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on October 12, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Talk on Graph Theory]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mnp-club.github.io//events/GraphTheory/" />
  <id>http://mnp-club.github.io//events/GraphTheory</id>
  <published>2016-09-24T04:48:04+05:30</published>
  <updated>2016-09-24T04:48:04+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Maths And Physics Club</name>
    <uri>http://mnp-club.github.io/</uri>
    <email>mnp-club-iitb@googlegroups.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;We started with a recap of the definition and various representations of graphs. We reviewed bi-partite graphs, n-partite graphs, planar graphs and trees. 
Cographs can be defined inductively as: a trivial graph is a cograph and a “disjoint union” or a “join” of two cographs is a cograph. Every cograph can be represented by a binary cotree (not unique) with leaf nodes as vertices and all internal nodes being labelled either as “disjoint union” or “join”. A graph is a cograph iff P3 (path of length 3) is not an induced subgraph. This characterization can be used to determine whether a graph is a cograph in linear time.
The cotree representation suggests a generalization of the class of cographs. As before, each vertex is a leaf node in the tree representation. Assign a label to each leaf node from a set of labels L. Now each internal node is a relation on L. Two leaf nodes are adjacent iff their labels are related by the relation defined by their least common ancestor in the tree representation. The special case where L is singleton gives us cographs. 
After this we looked at representing graph theoretic problems in first order and second order logic. Relation between complexity of solving a problem and complexity of stating a problem in a formal language was discussed. For example, all problems expressible in First Order logic have polynomial time algorithms (ie they are in P). Furthermore, Fagin showed in 1973 that the set of all properties expressible in existential second-order logic is precisely the complexity class NP! This suggests a new approach to P vs NP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graph (definition): &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Graph_theory#Graph&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;br /&gt;
Cographs : &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cograph&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Fagin’s theorem: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fagin%27s_theorem&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io//events/GraphTheory/&quot;&gt;Talk on Graph Theory&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io/&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on September 24, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Physics Detective]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mnp-club.github.io//events/physics-detective/" />
  <id>http://mnp-club.github.io//events/physics-detective</id>
  <published>2016-09-20T04:48:04+05:30</published>
  <updated>2016-09-20T04:48:04+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Maths And Physics Club</name>
    <uri>http://mnp-club.github.io/</uri>
    <email>mnp-club-iitb@googlegroups.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;h3 id=&quot;venue--new-yoga-room-old-sac&quot;&gt;Venue : New Yoga Room, Old SAC&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;date-september-19-2016&quot;&gt;Date: September 19, 2016&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-monday&quot;&gt;Day: Monday&lt;/h3&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io//events/physics-detective/&quot;&gt;Physics Detective&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io/&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on September 20, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lab Visit]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mnp-club.github.io//events/lab-visit-spacetime/" />
  <id>http://mnp-club.github.io//events/lab-visit-spacetime</id>
  <published>2016-09-04T04:47:25+05:30</published>
  <updated>2016-09-04T04:47:25+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Maths And Physics Club</name>
    <uri>http://mnp-club.github.io/</uri>
    <email>mnp-club-iitb@googlegroups.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;The Space-Time lab is IIT Bombay’s own super-computing facility.
The one of its kind laboratory in India, this super computing cluster consists of about 380 nodes with as many as 3040 processing cores, built using the most recent Intel quad core processors. The aggregate theoretical speed is expected to hover around 22 Tera-Flops. R. B. Sunoj sir will be present to tell us more about the lab!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find out more about the lab on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://spacetime.iitb.ac.in/index4.htm&quot;&gt;lab homepage&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;venue--old-cse-building&quot;&gt;Venue : Old CSE Building&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;date-september-3-2016&quot;&gt;Date: September 3, 2016&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-saturday&quot;&gt;Day: Saturday&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;time-630-pm&quot;&gt;Time: 6:30 pm&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We visited the SpaceTime High Performance Computing Lab IIT Bombay. The visit was both informative and inspiring. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chem.iitb.ac.in/people/Faculty/prof/rbs.html&quot;&gt;Professor Sunoj&lt;/a&gt; (Convener, SpaceTime HPC) and Mr. Trirag Chowdhury (SysAd, SpaceTime HPC) explained the various components and processes that must work harmoniously in order for the 22teraflop supercomputer to do it’s job. The main hardware required for the computing part are Master nodes and several Computing nodes. These nodes are designed to be able to function 24x7 with zero downtime. There’s a huge network of cables (total 6 Km in length!) beneath the floor that connects these nodes. Much of the remaining equipment is engaged in enabling the nodes to function properly, from power supply to cooling. For the facility to be function ceaselessly, redundancy and hot-standby are essential features in every aspect including data storage, cooling system, etc. To know more about the lab visit the &lt;a href=&quot;http://spacetime.iitb.ac.in/index4.htm&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This High Performance Computing facility was ranked 1st in India in 2009 and was among the top 500 in the world for two consecutive rankings. The facility is used by various departments in the institute. This lab is a brainchild of Professor Sunoj who worked dedicatedly towards building this facility overcoming numerous challenges on the way. The message he wanted to share with young minds of the day was that “If you think you can achieve it, no matter how big or risky, stand up for it. Give in your best, and realise that it can happen. It will.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over 130 professors across 14 departments in the department use this excellent facility for their HPC needs. Professor Sunoj also briefed us about how he was motivated to build a supercomputer in the campus to suffice his needs in Computational Molecular Chemistry. He is also spearheading the next 52 teraflop HPC installation in the institute ‘SpaceTime-X’ and is a part of the National Supercomputing Mission, with the vision to set up a 1500 teraflop cluster, catapulting India in the supercomputing race!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Images taken during the visit can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/folderview?id=0B-eOErpKeOmQU0ZrMmtzRTFPbXc&amp;amp;usp=sharing&quot;&gt;here!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io//events/lab-visit-spacetime/&quot;&gt;Lab Visit&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io/&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on September 04, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Documentary Screening]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mnp-club.github.io//events/documentary-screening-feynman/" />
  <id>http://mnp-club.github.io//events/documentary-screening-feynman</id>
  <published>2016-09-01T04:47:25+05:30</published>
  <updated>2016-09-01T04:47:25+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Maths And Physics Club</name>
    <uri>http://mnp-club.github.io/</uri>
    <email>mnp-club-iitb@googlegroups.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;h3 id=&quot;venue--fc-kohli-auditorium-kresit&quot;&gt;Venue : FC Kohli Auditorium, KReSIT&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;date-august-31-2016&quot;&gt;Date: August 31, 2016&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-wednesday&quot;&gt;Day: Wednesday&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;time-900-pm&quot;&gt;Time: 9:00 pm&lt;/h3&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io//events/documentary-screening-feynman/&quot;&gt;Documentary Screening&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io/&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on September 01, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Group Discussion]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mnp-club.github.io//events/gd-1/" />
  <id>http://mnp-club.github.io//events/gd-1</id>
  <published>2016-08-24T04:47:25+05:30</published>
  <updated>2016-08-24T04:47:25+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Maths And Physics Club</name>
    <uri>http://mnp-club.github.io/</uri>
    <email>mnp-club-iitb@googlegroups.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;The GD began with a very interesting game. The game is as follows,
It is a 2 player game: each player chooses a number from 1 - 9 and each number chosen should not be previously chosen by any of the two players. If the last three numbers adds to 15 the player wins. Does there exist a winning strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solution:&lt;/strong&gt; There is no winning strategy. Its analogous to playing tic-tac-toe on a magic square hence no solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;epr-paradox&quot;&gt;EPR Paradox&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we started discussing the EPR Paradox: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EPR_paradox&quot;&gt;Einstein-Podolsky-Rosen&lt;/a&gt; and gave the famous example of two particles starting from the same position and moving in the opposite direction such that the total momentum of the system in zero. Now the weird part of this is that if one measures the position of any one of the particles when both the particles are very far apart that transmission of information takes a significant time, we would know the position of the other particle too (by momentum conservation). Likewise, the measurement of position of the second system will determine the measurement of position of the first system, even though the systems are no longer physically linked in the traditional sense of local coupling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The act of measuring a observable of a system not only makes it’s wave function to collapse but even the wave function of the other system to collapse instantaneously. Here we see that the fundamental postulate of Special Theory of Relativity that there is a maximum speed of information to travel being violated. And hence the paradox.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also the famous example of entangled spins was discussed which can be read &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EPR_paradox&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;arrows-theorem&quot;&gt;Arrow’s Theorem&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discussion then continued to Arrow’s theorem where students gave the statement of the theorem and described the fair rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A basic statement of the theorem is as follows:
Arrow’s theorem says that if the decision-making body has at least two members and at least three options to decide among, then it is impossible to design a social welfare function that satisfies all these conditions (assumed to be reasonable requirement of a fair voting system) at once:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A simple description of the conditions/the fair rules are as follows
  * If every voter prefers alternative X over alternative Y, then the group prefers X over Y.
  * If every voter’s preference between X and Y remains unchanged, then the group’s preference between X and Y will also remain unchanged (even if voters’ preferences between other pairs like X and Z, Y and Z, or Z and W change).
  * There is no “dictator”: no single voter possesses the power to always determine the group’s preference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very interesting and simple informal proof is given &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arrow%27s_impossibility_theorem&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;maxwells-demon&quot;&gt;Maxwell’s Demon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discussion then was shifted to Maxwell’s demon. One can see the following video by khan academy in which he has described the problem very nicely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/aKRDvSZ-igA&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, dicussions led to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quantumcomplexity.org/tutorials/knowledge-is-power-the-energy-content-of-bits/&quot;&gt;Szilard’s Engine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ltp&quot;&gt;LTP&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time for some mind-boggling LTPs to puzzle the group. So one of the LTPs were as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;At an ancient museum, a burglary takes place. The thief was caught by the security and accused of the robbery. (Declaring him as the thief, we mean that he is the thief.) But according to the law, every citizen gets a chance to call his/her lawyer before trial or imprisonment. The thief calls his/her lawyer. The lawyer arrives and walks away with the thief,lawfully.!
So What happened exactly?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io//events/gd-1/&quot;&gt;Group Discussion&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io/&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on August 24, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Universe and Beyond!]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mnp-club.github.io//blog/universe/" />
  <id>http://mnp-club.github.io//blog/universe</id>
  <published>2016-08-20T15:49:07+05:30</published>
  <updated>2016-08-20T15:49:07+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Thariq Shanavas</name>
    <uri>http://mnp-club.github.io/</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Is our universe really infinite? If you keep going in some direction in a spacecraft will you see some magical force field and a sign board saying “End of the Universe, Keep Out!” (Or rather, keep in? :P). &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://ichef.bbci.co.uk/wwfeatures/wm/live/1280_640/images/live/p0/3x/sw/p03xsw49.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Universe&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can say for certain that the universe is either finite or infinite (Big deal, who can’t say that? But wait, there’s more to it!). In an infinite universe, you can go on and on in your spaceship and you’ll never come across a boundary – you’ll just see more stars, galaxies, and maybe get to see some extra-terrestrial life. However, in a finite universe, you won’t come across a boundary- you’ll end up exactly where you started! You can associate this funny behaviour with the curvature of space time. Physicists are not yet sure about the geometry of our universe – it can be open (infinite), closed (finite) or flat (we’ll get to that later!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before getting into more details, we need to be familiar with the concept of critical density – in an expanding universe, if its average density turns out to be higher than a particular ‘critical’ value, it would collapse under its own gravity. Otherwise, it could expand forever (Slightly reminiscent of the escape velocity of the Earth – if you throw something hard enough, it’ll never come back).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the exact geometry depends on the average density of the universe (This is predicted by the Friedmann equation, arguably the most important result in cosmology).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It so turns out that if the average density of the universe is greater than this particular critical density (around $ 9.47x10^{-27} Kg/m^3 $ ), it would result in a closed finite universe, and an infinite open universe otherwise. If the density exactly matches the critical density, the universe would be flat – you can say that the space ship will go on for ever, or that it will come to the point where it started after traveling for an infinite time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can draw a two dimensional analogy to the closed and open universe. The closed universe is like a sphere – you’ll end up where you started if you keep going ‘in a straight line’. Since we are able to observe this from a 3- dimensional geometry, we can see the curvature of the two dimensional space we cooked up – but any two dimensional beings in our two dimensional universe would not be able to detect the ‘curvature’. Now the two dimensional analogue of an open universe is a saddle shape.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/4/40/Saddle_point.png&quot; alt=&quot;Saddle&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, any two dimensional beings would not be able to detect the curvature of their universe, just as we are not able to see any possible curvature in our universe. The two dimensional analogy of the flat universe is, well, flat. We see something exceedingly interesting here – the flat universe supports Euclidean geometry. In curved geometries, non-Euclidean geometry prevails. For example, in a closed universe, the ratio of the circumference to the diameter of a circle need not be the familiar value of pi – to put it better, the ratio of the circumference to the diameter of a circle in a curved geometry need not satisfy the equation $ e^{ix} +1 = 0 $. Again, it’s difficult to imagine this in a curved 3 dimensional geometry, but it’s easier in a curved two dimensional space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since all distances are measured in the plane, the radius of the circle in the closed universe is more than that in a flat geometry, and less in an infinite geometry. The value of pi is, hence more than that for a Euclidean geometry in an open universe and less in a closed universe. The same result follows in a three dimensional curved geometry. Hard to believe, but true. (See the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Friedmann%E2%80%93Lema%C3%AEtre%E2%80%93Robertson%E2%80%93Walker_metric&quot;&gt;Riemann Walker metric&lt;/a&gt;, and the video below, which nicely explains it. It’s hard to intuitively understand the deviation of the value of pi from its familiar Euclidean value in three dimension, and is best described mathematically.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/n1kK5BjEh9E&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, the angles of a triangle need not add up to 180 0 . It is more than 180 0 for a closed geometry and less than that for an open one. The closed universe is said to have ‘Positive’ curvature and the open one has ’Negative’ curvature. The flat universe has zero curvature. The angles of a triangle sum up to exactly 180 0 in that case.
&lt;img src=&quot;http://wmap.gsfc.nasa.gov/media/990006/990006_2048.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Curvature&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So is our universe open, closed or flat? All you have to do is measure the density, right? Trouble is, the measured value of average density of the universe is extremely close to the calculated critical density (taking into account dark matter and dark energy). It is not yet possible to say with certainty whether the universe is flat, open or closed. The best measured value of the ‘density parameter’, or the ratio of the actual density of the universe to the critical density is often quoted as around. (Damn! In that case the universe could be flat, open or closed!). Well, at least that explains why Euclidean geometry seems to hold in real life, and the angles of a triangle seem to add up to a hundred and eighty degrees. The curvature of our present universe is too small to detect in a small scale - sort of like why we’re not able to see the curvature of the Earth from its surface. (But then again, if the universe was indeed strongly curved, would the curved geometry have seemed natural and intuitive to us? Would Euclidean geometry seem alien? We can only wonder…)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is the universe so ‘flat’? Why is the density parameter so close to one? (You might want to see this awesome video &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MTUsOWtxKKA&quot;&gt;&lt;u&gt;here&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  There are some exotic and beautiful ideas like the theory of inflation, which seek to explain this observation (Inflation is another story, for another day!). The idea of inflation explains the flatness problem, the horizon problem and some other peculiar observations. It also predicts the existence of other universes, with possibly different laws of physics, separated by high energy ‘False Vacuum’. But so far, inflation has not made any predictions which could be tested. (The Theory of General Relativity was accepted only after the gravitational lensing of the light from a distant star by the sun was experimentally observed. The lensing effect was predicted by GR long before it was ever observed). However, inflationary models of the early universe do predict large scale gravitational waves, which, if detected, could provide direct proof of inflation. (The recently detected gravitational waves were the result of a particularly violent astronomical event – the kind of gravitational waves predicted by inflationary models are far more feeble, and hence harder to detect.). That is another motivation for building highly sensitive gravitational wave detectors – an active area of research in experimental physics. Inflation is an elegant and beautiful idea, which many physicists are eager to accept – but due to the lack of observable predictions, it’s still more like an idea, and not a theorem. The next decade will undoubtedly see advances in gravitational wave astronomy, and possibly provide conformation for inflation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of you might have noticed that I have ignored dark energy completely here. Well, it has now been observed that the universe is currently expanding exponentially – for the past few billion years. Dark energy, like inflation, is also predicted to be the outcome of a field – but one much weaker than that caused inflation. But it is quite possible that the exponential expansion due to dark energy might come to an end, just like that of inflation did. (If I may venture to say, likely. Can’t expect that to happen anytime soon, though. Dark energy has been doing its funny business for at least the last few billion years. It is also quite possible that this exponential expansion can go on for ever, eliminating the possibility of a big crunch. So much for looking forward to the boom and fancy lights.) And whatever we dreamt up still holds true, the universe might be closed or open, hyperbolic or spherical, all depending on its current density. Neither inflation nor dark energy can ‘flip’ its geometry – merely push it towards flatness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Curious about the mathematical formalism of the Riemann Walker metric? Or the exact deviation of pi from its ‘Euclidean’ value? Dark energy and inflation? &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/open?id=0B89M-PMv8EXlRUozVW43RWJtTkE&quot;&gt; &lt;u&gt;Read on &lt;/u&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to find out more!&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io//blog/universe/&quot;&gt;The Universe and Beyond!&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io/&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on August 20, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bazinga! Maths]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mnp-club.github.io//events/bazinga-maths/" />
  <id>http://mnp-club.github.io//events/bazinga-maths</id>
  <published>2016-08-12T04:48:04+05:30</published>
  <updated>2016-08-12T04:48:04+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Maths And Physics Club</name>
    <uri>http://mnp-club.github.io/</uri>
    <email>mnp-club-iitb@googlegroups.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Bazinga Maths is a quiz where teams compete to solve an assortment of problems from buzzer round and paradox resolution questions to deep thought problems. While the solutions are based on elementary concepts, they’re sure to test your creativity and challenge your reasoning skills!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;venue--lh-101&quot;&gt;Venue : LH 101&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;date-11th-august&quot;&gt;Date: 11th August&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-thursday&quot;&gt;Day: Thursday&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;time-900-pm&quot;&gt;Time: 9:00 pm&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
table {
    border-collapse: collapse;
    width: 100%;
}

td, th {
    border: 1px solid #dddddd;
    text-align: left;
    padding: 8px;
}

tr:nth-child(even) {
    background-color: #dddddd;
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finalists 2016!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bazinga! Maths concluded with a bang - two hours of exciting problem solving, surreal explanations - topped with a nail-biting thumb-crunching finale, with the winners decided by the smallest of margins! We are proud to present the winners of this edition of Bazinga! Maths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td width=&quot;10%&quot;&gt; 1.
		&lt;td width=&quot;30%&quot;&gt; Shourya Pandey &lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td width=&quot;30%&quot;&gt; Anuj Shetty &lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td width=&quot;30%&quot;&gt; Vaibhav Bhosale &lt;/td&gt;
    
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td width=&quot;10%&quot;&gt; 2.
        &lt;td width=&quot;30%&quot;&gt; Kartik Patekar &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td width=&quot;30%&quot;&gt; Deepanshu Kush &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td width=&quot;30%&quot;&gt; Atharva Korde &lt;/td&gt;
    
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td width=&quot;10%&quot;&gt; 3.
        &lt;td width=&quot;30%&quot;&gt; Utkarsh Gupta &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td width=&quot;30%&quot;&gt; Sai Sandeep &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td width=&quot;30%&quot;&gt; Venkateshwara Rao Ch &lt;/td&gt;
    
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td width=&quot;10%&quot;&gt; 4.
        &lt;td width=&quot;30%&quot;&gt; Sharvik Mittal &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td width=&quot;30%&quot;&gt; Himanshu Gupta &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td width=&quot;30%&quot;&gt; Kunal Mittal &lt;/td&gt;
    

&lt;hr /&gt;
For all those who missed, follow &lt;u&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/open?id=0BzrafcdwRhiEaHhkdDhjeDd2VmM&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; this link &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/u&gt;to check out the format and questions the finalists faced in the quiz - from deep-thought questions to paradoxes and more! Hope you all had a fun time!  
&lt;br /&gt;
Keep Calm and Bazinga!
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io//events/bazinga-maths/&quot;&gt;Bazinga! Maths&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io/&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on August 12, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bazinga! Physics]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mnp-club.github.io//events/bazinga-physics/" />
  <id>http://mnp-club.github.io//events/bazinga-physics</id>
  <published>2016-08-11T04:47:54+05:30</published>
  <updated>2016-08-11T04:47:54+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Maths And Physics Club</name>
    <uri>http://mnp-club.github.io/</uri>
    <email>mnp-club-iitb@googlegroups.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Bazinga Physics is a 3 round quiz where the participant have to rack their brains and use simple intuitive physics concept to solve questions. The questions can be explaining a simple everyday phenomenon to solving some mind-bending thought experiment. Join in and lets enjoy the true essence of physics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;venue--lh-101&quot;&gt;Venue : LH 101&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;date-10th-august&quot;&gt;Date: 10th August&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-wednesday&quot;&gt;Day: Wednesday&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;time-900-pm&quot;&gt;Time: 9:00 pm&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
table {
    border-collapse: collapse;
    width: 100%;
}

td, th {
    border: 1px solid #dddddd;
    text-align: left;
    padding: 8px;
}

tr:nth-child(even) {
    background-color: #dddddd;
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Finalists 2016!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bazinga! Physics concluded with a bang - two hours of exciting reasoning, innovative explanations - topped with a nail-biting finale. We are proud to present the winners of this edition of Bazinga! Physics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
	&lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td width=&quot;10%&quot;&gt; 1.
		&lt;td width=&quot;30%&quot;&gt; Kartik Patekar &lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td width=&quot;30%&quot;&gt; Sheshansh Agrawal &lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;td width=&quot;30%&quot;&gt; Rohit Kumar Jena &lt;/td&gt;
    
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td width=&quot;10%&quot;&gt; 2.
        &lt;td width=&quot;30%&quot;&gt; Pranav Pable &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td width=&quot;30%&quot;&gt; Sanat Anand &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td width=&quot;30%&quot;&gt; Kumar Ayush &lt;/td&gt;
    
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td width=&quot;10%&quot;&gt; 3.
        &lt;td width=&quot;30%&quot;&gt; Yash Karnik &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td width=&quot;30%&quot;&gt; Himanshu Aswani &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td width=&quot;30%&quot;&gt; Anant Joshi &lt;/td&gt;
    
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td width=&quot;10%&quot;&gt; 4.
        &lt;td width=&quot;30%&quot;&gt; Siddharth Mehta &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td width=&quot;30%&quot;&gt; Arunabh Ghosh &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td width=&quot;30%&quot;&gt; Harsh Mundra &lt;/td&gt;
    

&lt;hr /&gt;
For all those who missed, follow &lt;u&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/0BzrafcdwRhiEMHY5bFFQYXFuWjN4VEtUTFBCRzB6VGFIVklj/view&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; this link &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/u&gt;to check out the format and questions the finalists faced in the quiz - from explanation to paradoxes and more! Hope you all had a fun time!  
&lt;br /&gt;
Keep Calm and Bazinga!
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io//events/bazinga-physics/&quot;&gt;Bazinga! Physics&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io/&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on August 11, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[STAB Orientation For The Freshmen]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mnp-club.github.io//events/stab-orientation/" />
  <id>http://mnp-club.github.io//events/stab-orientation</id>
  <published>2016-08-04T04:47:25+05:30</published>
  <updated>2016-08-04T04:47:25+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Maths And Physics Club</name>
    <uri>http://mnp-club.github.io/</uri>
    <email>mnp-club-iitb@googlegroups.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Orientation for the Freshman on the activities, culture, enthusiasm and achievements of the TECH society in IIT Bombay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;venue-lt-pcsa&quot;&gt;Venue: LT PCSA&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;date-3rd-august&quot;&gt;Date: 3rd August&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-wednesday&quot;&gt;Day: Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;time-500-pm&quot;&gt;Time: 5:00 pm&lt;/h2&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io//events/stab-orientation/&quot;&gt;STAB Orientation For The Freshmen&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io/&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on August 04, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Summer Of Science (SOS) Project Presentation]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mnp-club.github.io//events/sos-meetup/" />
  <id>http://mnp-club.github.io//events/sos-meetup</id>
  <published>2016-07-29T04:47:02+05:30</published>
  <updated>2016-07-29T04:47:02+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Maths And Physics Club</name>
    <uri>http://mnp-club.github.io/</uri>
    <email>mnp-club-iitb@googlegroups.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Informal Presentation of the Projects done by IIT Bombay students who took up Summer of Science Projects during the summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;venue--new-yoga-room-sac&quot;&gt;Venue : New Yoga Room, SAC&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;date-28th-july&quot;&gt;Date: 28th July&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-thursday&quot;&gt;Day: Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;time-900-pm&quot;&gt;Time: 9:00 pm&lt;/h2&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io//events/sos-meetup/&quot;&gt;Summer Of Science (SOS) Project Presentation&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io/&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on July 29, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Blackhole Information Paradox]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mnp-club.github.io//blog/blackhole-paradox/" />
  <id>http://mnp-club.github.io//blog/blackhole-paradox</id>
  <published>2016-07-24T15:49:07+05:30</published>
  <updated>2016-07-24T15:49:07+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Toshi Parmar</name>
    <uri>http://mnp-club.github.io/</uri>
    <email>toshi.tanu08@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Does the baffle still remain?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://space-facts.com/wp-content/uploads/black-hole.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Blackhole&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a talk given on Aug ‘15 at a conference held at Stockholm$^{[1]}$; Stephen Hawking, the well-celebrated british physicist, proposed a resolution of the infamous Information loss paradox, a child of his own theory of Hawking Radiation $^{[2][3]}$ that overturned the widely perpetuated belief that nothing escapes from a black hole’s event horizon. In the interim, this left most of his contemporaries bemused since his theory had no mathematical backbone. A rigorous paper$^{[4]}$ collaborated by Hawking, Malcolm &amp;amp; Strominger in the January of ‘16, humorously entitled ‘Soft Hair on Black Holes’, attempts to pave a mathematical map to resolve the paradox once and for all. But Hawking et al conclude$^{[4]}$ that they’ve just introduced fresh &amp;amp; concrete tools to address the paradox and a complete description still remains an open challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-exactly-is-the-paradox&quot;&gt;What exactly IS the paradox?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The information loss paradox is yet another acclaimed scenario where Quantum Mechanics, describing the subatomic world with the highest precision and General Relativity, equally successful at the cosmic scale, act stubbornly incompatible$^{[10]}$.
General Relativity implies that once a system ‘falls’$^{[5]}$ in the black hole, any information regarding the system can not affect an outside observer, thus for all practical purposes the information is irretrievable. Notice, that we use irretrievable instead of destroyed, i.e. it doesn’t posses a problem if the black hole remains an ever absorbing body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-hawking-radiation&quot;&gt;The Hawking Radiation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around 1975, due to a remarkable connection made by Hawking$^{[6]}$ and Beckenstein$^{[7]}$ between Thermodynamics, Quantum Mechanics and Black Holes, Hawking Radiation came into picture which collapsed the possibility of everlasting black holes to null.
Hawking Radiation stated that black holes, in fact, aren’t as black as we expected them to be. Courtesy to locally small quantum effects$^{[2]}$, (which are ignored in the process of formation and evolution of black holes since the radius of curvature of spacetime outside the event horizon is very large compared to the Planck length$^{[11]}$, the length scale on which quantum fluctuations of the metric are expected to be of order unity) add up to produce a significant effect over the lifetime of the Universe. This simply implies that any black hole will create and emit particles such as neutrinos or photons at just the rate that one would expect if the black hole of M solar masses was similar to a blackbody, with temperature of about $6 × 10^{-8}$/M kelvins$^{[8]}$.
The fact that a black hole will emit photons when none escape is indigestible.
In layman language$^{[9]}$, Quantum Mechanics capacitates a constant potential for “virtual” Particle - Antiparticle pair to be created and annihilated, leaving a net zero state. Same phenomenon at the knife edge of the event horizon permits a possibility when one escapes, while the other plunges immediately into the black hole. Rather than instant annihilation, the “virtual” particle becomes real and escapes; making a petty energy drain on the black hole. The rate at which the energy dissipates from a black hole of M solar masses spares a massive 1071M3 seconds$^{[8]}$ as any black hole’s life period. Any such black hole of mass less than 1015 g would have evaporated by now. Near the end of its life the rate of emission would be very high and about 1030 erg would be released in the last 0.1 s$^{[2]}$. This is a fairly small explosion by astronomical standards but it is equivalent to about 1 million 1 Mton hydrogen bombs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;aftermaths-of-hawking-radiation-theory&quot;&gt;Aftermaths of Hawking Radiation Theory&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to understand why the information loss paradox is a problem, we need first to understand what it is.
Let’s design a thought experiment where a quantum system in pure state enters a black hole. The no-hair (or more aptly, three-hair) theorem$^{[15]}$ compels Hawking radiation to be completely independent of the state of the quantum system entering the black hole. Because part of the information about the state of the system is lost down the hole, the final situation is represented by a density matrix$^{[11]}$ rather than a pure quantum state (which it was, originally). In quantum physics, a scattering matrix or S-matrix is a unitary matrix$^{[12]}$ that maps the scattering channels (the quantum states of system before or after the collision). The scenario could have been picturised as the initial pure state quantum system interacting with a boundary condition and the Hawking radiation as the final scattering channel. But since the transformation from a pure quantum state to a density matrix is non-unitary, this means there is no Scattering-matrix$^{[13]}$ for the process of black-hole formation and evaporation. Or to say, the black hole has performed a non-unitary transformation on the state of system!$^{[14]}$  As you may recall, non-unitary evolution is not allowed to occur naturally in quantum theory because it fails to preserve probability &amp;amp; reversibility.
In layman terms what we start with is a pure state and a black hole of mass M.  What we end up with is a mixed state and a black hole of mass M.  In transforming between a mixed state and a pure state, one must throw away information.  For instance, in our example we took a state described by a set of eigenvalues and coefficients, a large set of numbers, and transformed it into a state described by temperature, one number.  All the other structure of the state was lost in the transformation.
In the face of such evolution, quantum mechanics falls apart, and we are faced with a dilemma.  Do black holes really defy the tenets of quantum theory, or have we missed something in our thought experiment.
Thus, therein lies a paradox!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-way-ahead&quot;&gt;The Way Ahead&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Possible Solutions To The Fate of Black Holes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
There have been many proposed solutions to the paradox, each equally bewildering as another. They are generally classified first into radical options, which require a quantum theory of gravity which has large deviations from semi-classical physics on macroscopic scales, such as non-locality or endowing horizons with special properties not seen in the semiclassical approximation, and conservative options, which do not need such help. Among the conservative options, it is argued that restoring unitary evolution relies on elimination of singularities.$^{[16]}$&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hawking’s leads : Soft Hair on Black Holes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
AdS-CFT correspondence theory$^{[17]}$, a theory launched in 1993, brought what is called as a Holographic Principle into center play in string theory. Holographic principle bestows same properties to universe as its root word indicates, a dimensional reduction. A hologram, which we encounter is a 2-D representation of a 3-D object. Holographic principle was first introduced by G. ‘t Hooft in 1933 as an attempt to a solution to the Information loss paradox and the widely proclaimed war he and L. Susskind had waged against hawking’s earlier claims that information is indeed lost. ‘T Hooft opined$^{[18]}$ that the requirement that physical phenomena associated with gravitational collapse should be duly reconciled with the postulates of quantum mechanics implies that at a Planckian scale our world is not 3+1 dimensional. Rather, the observable degrees of freedom can best be described as if they were Boolean variables defined on a two-dimensional lattice, evolving with time. This observation, deduced from not much more than unitarity, entropy and counting arguments, implies severe restrictions on possible models of quantum gravity. This dimensional reduction implies more constraints than the freedom we have in constructing models. This is the main reason why so-far no completely consistent mathematical models of quantum black holes have been found.
A year later, L. Susskind published a paper, ‘The World as A Hologram’$^{[19]}$, backing up ‘t Hooft’s theory. In July ‘04 Hawking conceded the bet since the AdS/CFT correspondence has shown there is no information loss. Then Hawking set working on the question : How does the information of the quantum state of the infalling particles re-emerge in the outgoing radiation?$^{[1]}$ He proposes that the information is stored, not in the interior of the black hole (as one might expect), but on its boundary, the event horizon. This is a form of holography. Classically, a black hole is independent of its past history. This is also true in the quantum domain. How then can a black hole emit the information about the particles that fell in? The answer, as explained above, is that the information is stored in a supertranslation associated with the shift of the horizon that the ingoing particles caused (Ingoing particles increase the mass of the black hole resulting into an outward shift in the horizon).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;supertranslation&lt;/em&gt;, in layman terms, are the result of a kind of symmetry. In Strominger’s terms$^{[20]}$, Individual light rays can’t talk to each other—if you’re riding on a light ray, causality prevents you from talking to somebody riding on an adjacent light ray. So these light rays are not tethered together. You can slide them up and down relative to one another. That sliding is called a super-translation. It turns out that adding a soft graviton at the event horizon has an alternate description as a super-translation in which you move some of these light rays back and forth relative to one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;supertranslations&lt;/em&gt; form a hologram of the ingoing particles at the horizon(For each particle that goes in, a soft-graviton is added). Thus, the jargon soft hair. The varying shifts along each generator of the horizon leave an imprint on the outgoing particles in a chaotic but deterministic manner. There is no loss of information and Information can be recovered in principle, but it is lost for all practical purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;Bibliography&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/pdf/1509.01147v1.pdf&quot;&gt;The Information Paradox for Black Holes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[2] &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v248/n5443/abs/248030a0.html&quot;&gt;Black Hole Explosions?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[3] &lt;a href=&quot;http://inspirehep.net/record/101338?ln=en&quot;&gt;Particle Creation by Black Holes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[4] &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/pdf/1601.00921v1.pdf&quot;&gt;Soft Hair on Black Holes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[5] &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wikiwand.com/en/Event_horizon&quot;&gt;Event Horizon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[6] &lt;a href=&quot;http://journals.aps.org/prd/pdf/10.1103/PhysRevD.14.2460&quot;&gt;Breakdown of Predictability in Gravitational Collapse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[7] &lt;a href=&quot;http://journals.aps.org/prd/abstract/10.1103/PhysRevD.7.2333&quot;&gt;Black Holes &amp;amp; Entropy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[8] &lt;a href=&quot;http://math.ucr.edu/home/baez/physics/Relativity/BlackHoles/hawking.html&quot;&gt;Hawking Radiation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[9] &lt;a href=&quot;https://starguyspeaks.wordpress.com/2016/02/21/on-steven-hawkings-new-theory-of-black-holes/&quot;&gt;Wordpress Blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[10] &lt;a href=&quot;http://theory.caltech.edu/people/jhs/strings/str115.html&quot;&gt;The Final Contradiction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[11] &lt;a href=&quot;http://journals.aps.org/rmp/pdf/10.1103/RevModPhys.29.74&quot;&gt;Description of States in Quantum Mechanics by Density Matrix and Operator Techniques&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[12] &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wikiwand.com/en/Unitary_operator&quot;&gt;Unitary Operator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[13] &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wikiwand.com/en/S-matrix&quot;&gt;S-Matrix&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[14] &lt;a href=&quot;http://math.ucr.edu/home/baez/physics/Relativity/BlackHoles/info_loss.html&quot;&gt;Black Hole Information Loss Problem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[15] &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wikiwand.com/en/No-hair_theorem&quot;&gt;No-Hair Theorem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[16] &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/pdf/0901.3156v1.pdf&quot;&gt;Conservative solutions to the black hole Information loss problem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[17] &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/1501.00007.pdf&quot;&gt;The AdS/CFT Correspondence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[18] &lt;a href=&quot;http://xxx.lanl.gov/abs/gr-qc/9310026&quot;&gt;Dimensional Reduction in Quantum Gravity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[19] &lt;a href=&quot;http://xxx.lanl.gov/abs/hep-th/9409089&quot;&gt;The World as Hologram&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
[20] &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.scientificamerican.com/dark-star-diaries/stephen-hawking-s-new-black-hole-paper-translated-an-interview-with-co-author-andrew-strominger/&quot;&gt;Interview by co-author Andrew Strominger&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io//blog/blackhole-paradox/&quot;&gt;Blackhole Information Paradox&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io/&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on July 24, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Brain's Positioning System]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mnp-club.github.io//blog/brain-positioning/" />
  <id>http://mnp-club.github.io//blog/brain-positioning</id>
  <published>2016-06-06T05:31:22+05:30</published>
  <updated>2016-06-06T05:31:22+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Thariq Shanavas</name>
    <uri>http://mnp-club.github.io/</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;h2 id=&quot;ever-wondered-whats-happening-in-our-brains-when-we-get-lost-or-explore-a-new-place-the-nobel-prize-in-physiology-for-the-year-2014-was-awarded-for-some-of-the-answers-to-this-problem-which-had-been-puzzling-scientists-for-almost-a-century&quot;&gt;Ever wondered what’s happening in our brains when we get lost or explore a new place? The Nobel Prize in Physiology for the year 2014 was awarded for some of the answers to this problem which had been puzzling scientists for almost a century.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the GPS in our phones and cars, our brain has a sophisticated positioning system. The brain integrates sensory data and knowledge of our current position to judge where we are headed. Only when we are lost or suffer from neurodegenerative diseases do we realise how critical our positioning system is to our survival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tracking and positioning systems of the mammalian brain was being studied for a long time. For example, the simple roundworm (Caenorhabditis elegans), with just 302 neurons, finds its way around solely by olfactory signals. It follows the path of an increasing or decreasing odour gradient. Honeybees, on the other hand, calculate its position by integrating its direction and speed of movement, without keeping track of landmarks or external cues. Vertebrates have even more sophisticated positioning systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Recent research in the area reveal neural maps in the brains of mammals, which are collections of neurons which fire in specific patterns corresponding to the surroundings and the animal’s position in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2014 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/medicine/laureates/2014/advanced-medicineprize2014.pdf&quot;&gt;Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine&lt;/a&gt; was awarded to Dr. John M. O’Keefe, Dr. May-Britt Moser and Dr. Edvard I. Moser for their discoveries of nerve cells in the brain that enable a sense of place and navigation.
Until the 1930s, research done on lab mice in mazes led to the belief that they memorised a long sequence of lefts and rights to find their way around. Edward C Tolman, physiology professor at the University of California from 1918 to 1954, observed the animals take shortcuts or make detours that would not be expected had they just memorised one long sequence of behaviour. This led to the hypothesis that the rats formed a sort of mental map of its surroundings, corresponding to the spatial geometry around it. Tolman’s ideas remained controversial for decades.
His ideas did not gain much ground up until the 1950s, when it became possible to insert electrodes into the brains of awake mammals to record firing patterns of individual neurons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A cell fires when it triggers an action potential- a short change in the potential difference across the cell membrane.
Dr. John M. O’Keefe studied the brain’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hippocampus&quot;&gt;hippocampus&lt;/a&gt;, a region in the brain associated with memory and spatial navigation (On a side note, the Hippocampus is one of the first regions to be affected by the Alzheimer’s disease). He inserted electrodes into a rat’s Hippocampus, and noticed that certain cells fired when the rat was at a particular location. He called them ‘Place cells’. It was seen that the firing pattern of a handful of such place cells precisely identified the animal’s location. In 1978, O’Keefe and his colleague suggested that place cells were an integral part of the mental map Tolman envisaged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neuroscientists of that era speculated that the hippocampus was too far removed from the sensory cortex (The part of the brain which handles the sensory inputs) to process their information in any meaningful way that could be understood by simple electrodes. O’Keefe’s observations dashed that speculation. It was then hypothesised that the area where place cells were located, namely the CA1 region, in the hippocampus received its location cues from other parts of the hippocampus rather than directly from the sensory cortex.
To verify the hypothesis, O’Keefe and his colleagues disrupted the communication channels between the CA1 region and the region of the hippocampus known to feed information to the CA1. Surprisingly, the neurons in the CA1 fired as before, when the rat reached specific locations. The inescapable conclusion was that the CA1 received its location cues from the entorhinal cortex, an adjoining area of the brain with a direct interface with the hippocampus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Electrodes were inserted into the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Entorhinal_cortex&quot;&gt;entorhinal cortex&lt;/a&gt;, and the firing patterns studied. The cells over there fired much like the place cells, but a single cell also happened to fire at multiple locations! This observation was made in 2002.
By 2005, O’Keefe and his team observed something spectacular about the firing patterns- the locations at which one particular cell fired were the vertices of a regular hexagon! These cells were dubbed grid cells. It was soon apparent that the entire enclosure where the rat was kept was divided into hexagonal grids. As these grid cells were further studied, more patterns were observed- the grid cells in the dorsal side fires at compact hexagons, while those lower down in the ventral side fired at hexagons of larger edge. The different layers of grid cells in the entorhinal cortex fired at hexagons of different size, each layer forming one with approximately 1.4 times the edge length of the hexagon in the layer above. This is strongly reminiscent of the smaller squares and the bigger ones in the Cartesian coordinates.
For example, the top layer fired at hexagons 30 to 35 cm in length, the next layer at 42 to 49 cm, and so on. The lower layers represented hexagons several meters across.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Direction cells and Border cells were also discovered in the entorhinal cortex – the direction cells fire when the rodent faces a particular direction, and the border cells fire when the rat is facing a wall. The firing patterns seemed to reflect the distance from the wall or the edge of an enclosure. In 2008, another long sought out cell was discovered- the speed cells. The firing rates of these cells increased in proportion to its running speed. These cells were believed to provide the grid cells updated information on the rodent’s position.
It was observed that the place cells in the hippocampus rapidly assumes a new location to fire as soon as the rat was put in a new enclosure. However, the grid cells was found to fire at analogous positions in the new enclosure. The grid cells, in some sense, formed a coordinate system that did not change from one enclosure to the other. The firing patterns from the entorhinal cortex was imported to the hippocampus and used to link the place cells to a particular location.
It is now believed that the hippocampus stores not just the position, but also the events that occur at that particular place. Particulars about an event are fused with the coordinates and are laid down in the animal’s memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;However, the scientific world is still pretty much in the dark as to how this information is used by the rest of the brain’s systems or the evolutionary origins of this intricate mechanism. The location systems of the brain and the mechanisms of memory formation will undoubtedly be a fascinating area of research for many years to come.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io//blog/brain-positioning/&quot;&gt;Brain&#39;s Positioning System&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io/&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on June 06, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Memristors and the Future of Computing]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mnp-club.github.io//blog/memristors/" />
  <id>http://mnp-club.github.io//blog/memristors</id>
  <published>2016-05-31T15:49:07+05:30</published>
  <updated>2016-05-31T15:49:07+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Dhruv Ilesh Shah</name>
    <uri>http://mnp-club.github.io/</uri>
    <email>dhruv.ilesh@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Welcome the days of a new kind of electronic device.. All hail the memristor, a device that could revolutionarise the world of computing by implementing wonderful technology!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1965, Gordon Moore predicted that the number of transistors in a dense integrated circuit doubles approximately every two years, and since then every manufacturer has been fighting hard to keep up with the Moore’s Law. With the scale of transistor entering sub-20nm, this number is saturating and Moore’s Law has begun to fail us. So what have the scientists and researchers got us? Behold the &lt;i&gt; &lt;b&gt;Memristor&lt;/b&gt;  (a portmanteau of the words memory and resistor)!&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original concept for memristors, as conceived in 1971 by Professor Leon Chua at the University of California, Berkeley, was a passive, non-linear, two-terminal electrical component that linked electric charge and magnetic flux. Since then, the definition of memristor has been broadened to include any form of non-volatile memory that is based on resistance switching, which increases the flow of current in one direction and decreases the flow of current in the opposite direction and has since then been thought of as the fourth fundamental electrical component.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Memristors constitute a special type of memory, called the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Resistive_random-access_memory&quot;&gt; ReRAM &lt;/a&gt; or resistive RAM, which works by altering the resistance across a dielectric. The outlook of memristors as memory devices started in 1996, when Stanley Williams, the founding director of the Quantum Science Research Laboratory at Hewlett-Packard, began to look for memory devices that are defect intolerant at the nano scale. And what better way to make a device defect-intolerant than too employ the defects themselves for the job!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; How Memristors Work :&lt;/b&gt; Instead of electrons, memristors use ions as the means of storing information. As the current passes, the holes and defects enable ions of informations to pass through with much greater speed and efficiency - way beyond 1 and 0, to 2, 3 and so on. These levels can be treated as distinct and the demarcation be carried out with ease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; What Does This Mean? &lt;/b&gt; At a lower power consumption than a transistor, a memristor can have multiple levels of representing data (upto 6 levels have been achieved), thus reducing the number of memristors required to perform the same task and who knows - the computer may actually become equipped with base-10 memory soon enough! For example, the largest unsigned binary 64-bit ­integer—18,446,744,073,709,551,615—could be held in 20 bits instead of 64. This not only reduces the number of transistors used, but also the complexity of circuits and ease of NLP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A memristor is often compared to an imaginary pipe that carries water. When the water flows in one direction, the pipe’s diameter expands and allows the water to flow faster – but when the water flows in the opposite direction, the pipe’s diameter contracts and slows the water’s flow down. If the water is shut off, the pipe retains its diameter until the water is turned back on. To continue the analogy, when a  memristor’s power is shut off, the memristor retains its resistance value. This would mean that if power to a computer was cut off with a hard shut down,  all the applications and documents that were open before the shut down would still be right there the screen when the computer was restarted. Isn’t that cool? Although we have been able to cut down the leakage current in conventional transistors, we cannot dare imagine making them as efficient as a prototype of a memristor! This would mean a big revolution in computing, and the best part is that it could be market-ready much before Quantum Computers (which use qubits to store more data-per-bit).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To see how the non-volatile nature and resistive-switching is achieved, check out this video by Stanley Williams: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rvA5r4LtVnc&quot;&gt; The 6 Minute Memristor Guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact Hewlett-Packard has a whole unit devoted to developing ‘The Machine’, &lt;em&gt;using electrons for processing, photons for communication, and ions for storage&lt;/em&gt;, expected to be completed by 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jennifer Rupp, a Professor of electrochemical materials at ETH Zurich,is working with IBM to build a memristor-based machine. Memristors, she points out, function in a way that is similar to a human brain: “Unlike a transistor, which is based on binary codes, a memristor can have multi-levels. You could have several states, let’s say zero, one half, one quarter, one third, and so on, and that gives us a very powerful new perspective on how our computers may develop in the future,” she says.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such a shift in computing methodology would allow us to create “smart” computers that operate in a way reminiscent of the synapses in our brains. Free from the limitations of the 0s and 1s, these more powerful computers would be able to learn and make decisions, ultimately getting us one step closer to creating human-like artificial intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;The outcome of this revolution would only be evident by the next decade, but the fact that nano-electronics has enabled us to revolutionarise the micro-electronics industry is a clear signal - to cope up with our growing computing needs, to explore the vastness of Universe, the path goes from within the Nano World! Memristors and Qubits are all set to power the upcoming generations in unfolding the mysteries of our creation, existence and the universe (multiple of them, in fact!)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io//blog/memristors/&quot;&gt;Memristors and the Future of Computing&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io/&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on May 31, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Flexagons]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://mnp-club.github.io//blog/flexagons/" />
  <id>http://mnp-club.github.io//blog/flexagons</id>
  <published>2016-05-04T15:49:07+05:30</published>
  <updated>2016-05-04T15:49:07+05:30</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Parth Jatakia</name>
    <uri>http://mnp-club.github.io/</uri>
    <email>parth.jatakia@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Flexagons are paper polygons, folded from straight or crooked strips of paper, which have the fascinating property of changing their faces when they are “flexed”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It all began in the fall of 1939. Arthur H. Stone, a 23-year-old graduate student from England, in residence at Princeton University on a mathematics fellowship, had just trimmed an inch from his American notebook sheets to make them fit his English binder. For amusement he began to fold the trimmed-off strips of paper in various ways, and one of the figures he made turned out to be particularly intriguing.
Here’s the video to make a simple hexaflexagon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt; &lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/VIVIegSt81k&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point Stone found the structure so interesting that he showed his paper models to friends in the graduate school. Soon “flexagons” were appearing in profusion at the lunch and dinner tables. A “Flexagon Committee” was organized to probe further into the mysteries of flexigation. The other members besides Stone were Bryant Tuckerman, a graduate student of mathematics; Richard P. Feynman, a graduate student in physics; and John W. Tukey, a young mathematics instructor.
Tuckerman quickly discovered that the simplest way to bring out all the faces of any flexagon was to keep flexing it at the same corner until it refused to open, then to shift to an adjacent corner. This procedure, known as the “Tuckerman traverse,” will bring up the six faces of a hexahexa in a cycle of 12 flexes, but 1,2 and 3 turn up three times as often as 4, 5 and 6. A convenient way to diagram a Tuckerman traverse is shown in Figure 4, the arrows indicating the order in which the faces are brought into view. This type of diagram can be applied usefully to the traversing of any type of flexagon. When the model is turned over, a Tuckerman traverse runs the same cycle in reverse order.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/-duGlEV1ddCw/VymMKE9pabI/AAAAAAAAC3c/XlD-a4OvfcE26j6P_9Ya0Ia2gcMR_1AEQCLcB/s1600/flexagon.png&quot; alt=&quot;Flexagon&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The video below gives a great visual explanation of the above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt; &lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/paQ10POrZh8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now after trying out the simple ones, if you’d want to achieve pro level…..These are some documents you can refer to!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A mathematical investigation of Flexagons can be found here: &lt;a href=&quot;http://delta.cs.cinvestav.mx/~mcintosh/comun/tflexagon/tflexagon.pdf&quot;&gt;Theory of Flexagons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also details about more complicated structures can be found out in the following link. Also you will find some papers written on flexagon on this website (though written in russian).: http://www.flexagon.net/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also if you are a foodie this video will be a heaven for you..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/GTwrVAbV56o&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io//blog/flexagons/&quot;&gt;Flexagons&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Maths And Physics Club at &lt;a href=&quot;http://mnp-club.github.io/&quot;&gt;Maths & Physics Club&lt;/a&gt; on May 04, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
  </content>
</entry>

</feed>